BRIEF OVERVIEW

I'm an experienced cognitive neuroscientist with a special interest in the measurement and characterization of neural dynamics, including the functional role of neural rhythms in cognition. I'm passionate about neuroscientific tool development and open science.



DR. RER. NAT. JULIAN Q. **KOSCIESSA**



kosciessa@mpib-berlin.mpg.de

ORCID: 0000-0002-4553-2794

Web: juliankosciessa.eu

EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Researcher 2020 - PRESENT Max Planck Institute for Human Development Berlin, Germany 2016 - 2020 **Predoctoral Research Fellow** IMPRS Comp2Psych Max Planck UCL Center for Computational Psychiatry and Aging Berlin, Germany 2010 - 2016 Research Assistant/Intern

Berlin, Germany

EDUCATION

Singapore, Singapore

London, UK

Humboldt Universität zu Berlin 2016 - 2020 Psychology Dr. rer. nat. (summa cum laude) 2014 - 2016 Humboldt Universität zu Berlin Mind & Brain - Track Brain M.Sc. (GPA: 1.0) 2011 - 2014 Freie Universität Berlin

Psychology B.Sc. Bachelor of Science (GPA: 1.1)

EXPERTISE

MATLAB	Python	_
R	English	
UNIX	Mandarin	

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

07/2020 - PRESENT **Postdoctoral Researcher**

Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany

10/2016 - 03/2020 **Predoctoral Research Fellow**

IMPRS COMP2PSYCH

Max Planck UCL Center for Computational Psychiatry and Aging Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany

Lifespan Neural Dynamics Group

Supervisors: Prof. Dr. Ulman Lindenberger, Dr. Douglas D. Garrett

10/2015 - 03/2016 Research Intern

> UCL Institute of Cognitive Neuroscience Pls: Prof. Emrah Düzel & Prof. Ray Dolan Supervisor: Dr. Dorothea Hämmerer

03/2015 - 07/2015 Research Intern

Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany

Center for Adaptive Rationality (ARC) Supervisor: Dr. Wouter van den Bos

09/2012 - 09/2013 **Research Assistant**

07/2014 - 09/2015 Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany

04/2016 - 09/2016 Cognitive and neuronal dynamics of memory across the lifespan

Supervisors: Dr. Markus Werkle-Bergner & Dr. Yee Lee Shing

01/2014 - 05/2014 Research Intern

Cognitive Neuroscience Laboratory, Duke-NUS, Singapore

PI: Prof. Michael Chee

Supervisor: Dr. Irma Kurniawan

EDUCATION

10/2016 - 10/2020 Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

> Doctoral student: Psychology Dr. rer. nat. (summa cum laude)

Dissertation: Measurement and relevance of rhythmic and aperiodic

human brain dynamics

10/2014 - 09/2016 Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

> Master's student: Mind & Brain - Track Brain Degree: M.Sc. Master of Science (GPA: 1.0)

Thesis: Effects of short-term memory load and task training on the amplitude and abundance of rhythmic neural activity (1.0) Supervisors: Dr. Markus Werkle-Bergner, Prof. Dr. Werner Sommer

09/2015 - 04/2016 **University College London**

Two Erasmus exchange terms; Institute of Neurology

07/2013 - 05/2014 National University of Singapore (NUS)

Two exchange semesters; Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences

10/2011 - 09/2014

Freie Universität Berlin

Bachelor's student: Psychology

Degree: B.Sc. Bachelor of Science (GPA: 1.1)

Thesis: The assessment of microsaccades from the rEOG (1.0)

Supervisors: Dr. Markus Werkle-Bergner, Prof. Dr. Michael Niedeggen

PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- Kloosterman, N. A., Kosciessa, J. Q., Lindenberger, U., Fahrenfort, J. J., & Garrett, D. D. (2020). Boosts in brain signal variability track liberal shifts in decision bias. Elife, 9. doi:10.7554/ eLife.54201
- Kosciessa, J. Q., Kloosterman, N. A., & Garrett, D. D. (2020). Standard multiscale entropy reflects neural dynamics at mismatched temporal scales: What's signal irregularity got to do with it? PLoS Computational Biology, 16(5), e1007885. doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007885
- Kosciessa, J. Q., Grandy, T. H., Garrett, D. D., & Werkle-Bergner, M. (2020). Single-trial characterization of neural rhythms: Potential and challenges. NeuroImage, 206, 116331. doi:10.1016/j.neuroimage.2019.116331
- Hämmerer, D., Callaghan, M. F., Hopkins, A., Kosciessa, J., Betts, M., Cardenas-Blanco, A., Kanowski, M., Weiskopf, N., Dayan, P., Dolan, R. J., & Düzel, E. (2018). Locus coeruleus integrity in old age is selectively related to memories linked with salient negative events. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 115, 2228-2233. doi:10.1073/pnas.1712268115

PREPRINTS

Kosciessa, J. Q., Lindenberger, U. & Garrett, D. D. (2020). Thalamocortical excitability adjustments guide human perception under uncertainty. Under revision at Nature Communications.

MONOGRAPHS/THESES

- Kosciessa, J. Q. (2020, Dr. rer. nat.). Measurement and relevance of rhythmic and aperiodic human brain dynamics. Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin. doi:10.18452/22040
- Kosciessa, J. Q. (2016, M. Sc.). Effects of short-term memory load and task training on the amplitude and abundance of rhythmic neural activity. Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin
- Kosciessa, J. (2014, B. Sc.). The assessment of microsaccades from the rEOG. Freie Universität

POSTERS (SELECTED)

- Kosciessa, J. Q., & Garrett, D. D. (2019, accepted). Multimodal signatures of selective attention dynamics across the adult lifespan. Poster presented at OHBM 2019: Rome, Italy.
- Perry, A. *, Kosciessa, J. Q.*, Polk, S., Garrett, D.D. (2019). Aging-related differences in the structural and functional basis of attentional flexibility. Poster presented at OHBM 2019: Rome, Italy. (* joint contributions)
- Kosciessa, J. Q., & Garrett, D. D. (2018). Thalamocortical BOLD variability reflects network integration and alpha rhythms. Poster presented at Interpreting BOLD: Furthering the dialogue between cellular and cognitive neuroscience. Oxford, UK.
- Kosciessa, J. Q., & Garrett, D. D. (2018). Neural rhythm dynamics during rapid attentional switching. Poster presented at CuttingEEG. Paris, France.
- Kosciessa, J. Q., Grandy, T. H., Garrett, D. D., & Werkle-Bergner, M. (2018). Single-trial oscillation detection reveals stable inter-individual differences in rhythmicity. Poster presented at Organization for Human Brain Mapping Meeting 2018. Singapore, Singapore.
- Kosciessa, J. Q., Grandy, T.H., Werkle-Bergner, M. (2017). Towards a single-trial characterization of neural rhythms. Poster presented at CuttingEEG 2017, Glasgow, UK.

TEACHING & TALKS (SELECTED)

- 2020 (postponed to 2021): Invited symposium talk ("Influences of arousal and cortical excitability on adaptive perceptual decision making"): "Humans dynamically adjust sensory excitability to guide perceptual decisions". International Conference of Cognitive Neuroscience. Helsinki, Finland
- 2020: Invited Colloqium Talk: "Measurement and relevance of rhythmic and aperiodic human brain dynamics". Biopsychologie und Neuroergonomie. Technische Universitat Berlin
- 2020: Invited Methods workshop: "Multi-scale entropy as a tool to characterize neural signal irregularity". EEG Meeting Series. Max Planck Institute for Human Development.
- 2018: Invited LIFE Seminar: "Methods for the analysis of rhythmic and arrhythmic brain activity". Max Planck Institute for Human Development. Berlin, Germany

FUNDING & AWARDS

2018: IBRO Poster Award Interpreting BOLD 2018

2018: DAAD Conference Travel Grant to Interpreting BOLD 2018 (Oxford, UK)

2015/2016: DAAD Erasmus Stipend (University College London, UK)

2014: DAAD PROMOS Stipend (National University Singapore, Singapore)

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITES

Peer-review:

PNAS, Brain Topography, European Journal of Neuroscience, Neurolmage, PLOS One Member of the Organization for Human Brain Mapping (OHBM)